<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>GEAS — Alice Kober Gesellschaft für die Entzifferung Antiker Schriftsysteme</title><link>/</link><description>Recent content on GEAS — Alice Kober Gesellschaft für die Entzifferung Antiker Schriftsysteme</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>/contributors/michael_m%C3%A4der/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/contributors/michael_m%C3%A4der/</guid><description/></item><item><title/><link>/contributors/stephan_balmer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/contributors/stephan_balmer/</guid><description/></item><item><title/><link>/contributors/elisa_schmutz/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/contributors/elisa_schmutz/</guid><description/></item><item><title/><link>/contributors/nicolai_rawyler/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/contributors/nicolai_rawyler/</guid><description/></item><item><title/><link>/contributors/simon_plachtzik/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/contributors/simon_plachtzik/</guid><description/></item><item><title/><link>/contributors/christian_prager/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/contributors/christian_prager/</guid><description/></item><item><title/><link>/contributors/emma_van_den_bold/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/contributors/emma_van_den_bold/</guid><description/></item><item><title>GEAS claims breakthrough by means of Experimental Script Archaeology, Part II: The emergence of 'runic' sign forms through the Rahmenquader Effect</title><link>/news/2025-01-01-experimental-archaeology-ii_rahmenquader-effect/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2025-01-01-experimental-archaeology-ii_rahmenquader-effect/</guid><description>Besides the proposal for the development of the futhark order (cf. part I), the GEAS Rune Provenance Theory contains other micro-theses to explain unsolved problems within the Rune transfer question. One more of these explanations – the Rahmenquader Effect, could be given solely due to the Reitia Alphabet Learning Procedure reappraised by actors of the &amp;ldquo;Iluis Glanna&amp;rdquo; Celtic Reenactment Clan on the occasion of the 2021 Historical Handcraft Market in Huttwil, Switzerland.</description></item><item><title>GEAS claims breakthrough by means of Experimental Script Archaeology, Part I: The origin of the futhark order</title><link>/news/2024-12-01-experimental-archaeology-i_futhark-order/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2024-12-01-experimental-archaeology-i_futhark-order/</guid><description>In the past years, two things have changed in regard to the long-lasting debate on the provenance of runic writing: At the one hand, Old European alphabets have been examined more thoroughly than ever, using modern paleographic methods in projects such as TIR, LexLep and PQN. At the other hand, archaeology has shown that North Italic writing was in use much longer than previously assumed, i.e. up to the 2nd century AD (see chapter 1.</description></item><item><title>The GEAS Rune Provenance Theory: A Response to every single question as to how writing emerged in Germania</title><link>/news/2024-11-01-the-geas-rune-provenance-theory/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2024-11-01-the-geas-rune-provenance-theory/</guid><description>The GEAS RPT is a multi-disciplinary long-term endeavour envisaging an overall theory of the genesis of runic writing. The outline of parts 1 to 4 presented below gives insight into the content of the following publications:
Mäder, Michael (im Druck): „Der Fura-zara-kara-Merkspruch, der Rahmenquader-Effekt und ein alter Knoblauchkult: Die Übernahme des Futhark aus den norditalischen Alphabetritualen.“ Tagungsband ’Functions of Runic Literacy 200 to 1500 AD. Ninth International Symposium on Runes and Runic Inscriptions (ISRRI), Akademie Sankelmark, Germany, 14-19 June 2022’ (Runrön 26).</description></item><item><title>Paleografia Quantitativa Norditalica (PQN): Massing some evidence, Missing some conference</title><link>/news/2023-08-01-paleografia-quantitativa-norditalica/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2023-08-01-paleografia-quantitativa-norditalica/</guid><description>The collective GEAS project called PQN (Paleografia Quantitativa Norditalica) depicts every single graphic shape of the Lepontic/Brembonic/Cisalpine-Celtic, Raetic/Camunic, and Etruscan/Lemnic sub-alphabets&amp;hellip;. and the Elder Futhark.
Excerpt from the 40-page long PQN tables with several thousand sign variants in North Italic and Germanic writing. Graphemes which are identical according to the GEAS standards are listed on the same line. From the 125 listed variants of runes, 76 are identical, 49 are similar and none is different.</description></item><item><title>Byblos Script: First sound value proposal ever based on external (iconographic) evidence</title><link>/news/2023-07-01-byblos-first-sound-value-proposal/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2023-07-01-byblos-first-sound-value-proposal/</guid><description>In an article soon to be published in Ugarit Forschungen, M. Mäder will suggest the first two sound value proposals for the Byblos Syllabary ever achieved by external evidence. A cylinder seal published by Garbini in 2004, depicting the three daughters of Achenaton and Nofretete together with three names written in Byblos script attached to them, is compared to the Berlin Familienstele showing the exact same scene, with the names written in Egyptian Hieroglyphs.</description></item><item><title>Linking Leponticon and Raeticon to Lexicon Leponticum and Thesaurus Inscriptionum Raeticarum</title><link>/news/2021-07-01-linking-leponticon-and-raeticon/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2021-07-01-linking-leponticon-and-raeticon/</guid><description>It is our duty to provide photographs to every inscription depicted in the GEAS Corpora. But in the case of Lepontic and Raetic, this would be double work. Instead of collecting and rendering images for each of the more than 600 inscripitons unicodified by GEAS, we decided to link each of the Leponticon and Raeticon inscriptions to the respective entrance in [LexLep] (https://lexlep.univie.ac.at/wiki/Main_Page) and [TIR] (https://tir.univie.ac.at/wiki/Main_Page). By clicking to the inscripiton’s sigla, the GEAS user gets immediate access to all the informations and literature presented in the Vienna corpora.</description></item><item><title>James Hoch (1990) confirmed: The Byblos syllabary is indeed adopted from the Egyptian Consonant Alphabet</title><link>/news/2021-03-01-james-hoch-1990-confirmed/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2021-03-01-james-hoch-1990-confirmed/</guid><description>Back in 2017, Marwan Kilani pushed us to new realms by recommending Harvey Sobelman’s (1961) n-gram analysis and James Hoch’s (1990) suggestion of comparing the Byblos script to the Egyptian phonographic (consonantial) sub-alphabet. Departing from the successful sound value attribution of ;  pa compared to p3 in Anchesen-pa-Aton’s hieroglyphic name on the Berlin Familienstele, combined with the proposal of the logo-phonograms  ATON and  AMUN (the latter being used on the historisizing Garbini (2004) seal, because Anchesen-pa-Aton changed her name into Anchesen-pa-Amun in late Amarna period), the show must now go on.</description></item><item><title>Does Brian Colless refuse the  me-ke-t-ATON ≈  me-ri-t-ATON proposal?</title><link>/news/2019-09-01-brian-colless-refuses-geas-proposals/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2019-09-01-brian-colless-refuses-geas-proposals/</guid><description>We appreciate Brian Colless’ great and almost live-long efforts and contributions to the deipherment of the Byblos syllabary, and we agree that IF one of the former claims for full decipherment should be partially taken for serious, then it is clearly Mendenhall’s (1985) work, who integrates Dunanats (1945) basic observations better and more cautiously than anyone since and before. And, to be honest, several inscriptions could only be included into the [Byblicon Online Corpus of Byblos Inscriptions] (https://center-for-decipherment.</description></item><item><title/><link>/jobs/2021-sommerpraktikum-datenbearbeitung/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/jobs/2021-sommerpraktikum-datenbearbeitung/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Corpus Statistics and Concordance List for Linear Elamite – Supplement to the OCLEI (Online Corpus of Elamite Inscriptions)</title><link>/journal/2020_01__balmer-et-al__corpus-statistics-and-concordance-list-oclei/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/journal/2020_01__balmer-et-al__corpus-statistics-and-concordance-list-oclei/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Das Syllabar der elamischen Strichschrift – Eine Zeichenanalyse</title><link>/journal/2017_01__plachtzik-et-al__das-syllabar-der-elamischen-strichschrift/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/journal/2017_01__plachtzik-et-al__das-syllabar-der-elamischen-strichschrift/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Digital Corpus of Cuneiform Elamite Transliterations (DCCET) without the Achaemenid Elamite Texts</title><link>/journal/2018_01__van-den-bold-et-al__digital-corpus-of-cuneiform-elamite-transliterations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/journal/2018_01__van-den-bold-et-al__digital-corpus-of-cuneiform-elamite-transliterations/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Paleografia quantitativa norditalica: Segni e varianti negli alfabeti retico-camuno, leponzio ed etrusco-venetico, con una comparazione alle rune del Futhark antico</title><link>/journal/2023_01__maeder__paleografia-quantitativa-norditalica/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/journal/2023_01__maeder__paleografia-quantitativa-norditalica/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Proto- und Linear-Elamisch: Formaler Vergleich, Berechnung des Jaccard-Index und Identifikation einer Übergangsphase</title><link>/journal/2021_01__maeder__proto-und-linear-elamisch/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/journal/2021_01__maeder__proto-und-linear-elamisch/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Zur Homophonie der Schmetterlingszeichen im Linear-Elamischen</title><link>/journal/2016_01__higson__zur-homophonie-der-schmetterlingszeichen/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/journal/2016_01__higson__zur-homophonie-der-schmetterlingszeichen/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>