<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Northitalic on GEAS — Alice Kober Gesellschaft für die Entzifferung Antiker Schriftsysteme</title><link>/tags/northitalic/</link><description>Recent content in Northitalic on GEAS — Alice Kober Gesellschaft für die Entzifferung Antiker Schriftsysteme</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/northitalic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>GEAS claims breakthrough by means of Experimental Script Archaeology, Part II: The emergence of 'runic' sign forms through the Rahmenquader Effect</title><link>/news/2025-01-01-experimental-archaeology-ii_rahmenquader-effect/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2025-01-01-experimental-archaeology-ii_rahmenquader-effect/</guid><description>Besides the proposal for the development of the futhark order (cf. part I), the GEAS Rune Provenance Theory contains other micro-theses to explain unsolved problems within the Rune transfer question. One more of these explanations – the Rahmenquader Effect, could be given solely due to the Reitia Alphabet Learning Procedure reappraised by actors of the &amp;ldquo;Iluis Glanna&amp;rdquo; Celtic Reenactment Clan on the occasion of the 2021 Historical Handcraft Market in Huttwil, Switzerland.</description></item><item><title>GEAS claims breakthrough by means of Experimental Script Archaeology, Part I: The origin of the futhark order</title><link>/news/2024-12-01-experimental-archaeology-i_futhark-order/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2024-12-01-experimental-archaeology-i_futhark-order/</guid><description>In the past years, two things have changed in regard to the long-lasting debate on the provenance of runic writing: At the one hand, Old European alphabets have been examined more thoroughly than ever, using modern paleographic methods in projects such as TIR, LexLep and PQN. At the other hand, archaeology has shown that North Italic writing was in use much longer than previously assumed, i.e. up to the 2nd century AD (see chapter 1.</description></item><item><title>The GEAS Rune Provenance Theory: A Response to every single question as to how writing emerged in Germania</title><link>/news/2024-11-01-the-geas-rune-provenance-theory/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2024-11-01-the-geas-rune-provenance-theory/</guid><description>The GEAS RPT is a multi-disciplinary long-term endeavour envisaging an overall theory of the genesis of runic writing. The outline of parts 1 to 4 presented below gives insight into the content of the following publications:
Mäder, Michael (im Druck): „Der Fura-zara-kara-Merkspruch, der Rahmenquader-Effekt und ein alter Knoblauchkult: Die Übernahme des Futhark aus den norditalischen Alphabetritualen.“ Tagungsband ’Functions of Runic Literacy 200 to 1500 AD. Ninth International Symposium on Runes and Runic Inscriptions (ISRRI), Akademie Sankelmark, Germany, 14-19 June 2022’ (Runrön 26).</description></item><item><title>Paleografia Quantitativa Norditalica (PQN): Massing some evidence, Missing some conference</title><link>/news/2023-08-01-paleografia-quantitativa-norditalica/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2023-08-01-paleografia-quantitativa-norditalica/</guid><description>The collective GEAS project called PQN (Paleografia Quantitativa Norditalica) depicts every single graphic shape of the Lepontic/Brembonic/Cisalpine-Celtic, Raetic/Camunic, and Etruscan/Lemnic sub-alphabets&amp;hellip;. and the Elder Futhark.
The decision to include Germanic writing will potentially lead the Rune provenance question to unexplored terrain. Spoiler ante publicationis: Of the 24 Elder Futhark main types, 21 have identical shapes to graphic variants from North Italic Alphabets, with 13 of them also representing identical sound values, and a further 8 representing similar sound values (i.</description></item></channel></rss>